<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Adrian Rubio</title>
    <description>This is my blog where I share my coding journey, my experiences, challenges, and discoveries in the ever-evolving world of programming.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 10:58:05 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2025 10:58:05 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.3.2</generator><item>
        <title>ESP32 Environment Monitor</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! During this past month after Shipwrecked, I have built an ESP32 environment monitor, completed a hardware project with my dad, and started a very interesting project with my brother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main thing I worked on this past month was my ESP32 environment monitor. I designed the circuit in Fritzing instead of Tinkercad because it had the sensors I needed. I was initially going to use a DHT22 and an MQ135, but decided that the BME280 and the SGP30 were more efficient and gave more accurate readings. The advantage of the BME280 over the DHT22 is that it measures temperature, humidity, altitude, and pressure, while the DHT22 only measures temperature and humidity. For the gas sensor, I decided to use the SGP30 because its readings are much more accurate than the MQ135. I decided to use an ESP32 because I wanted to display the readings both on a web page over the house WiFi and on an LCD screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a week of iterating through different possible designs, I ended up with one I was quite happy with and decided to build it once I had all the parts. The two sensors required pin soldering, but unfortunately the SGP30 didn’t work. I still don’t know if it was faulty out of the box or if my soldering somehow damaged the sensor. We had to buy a replacement, but thankfully this one worked perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/esp32-environment-monitor/esp32-environment-monitor.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the project was functional, I made some final touches to the code. Soon I had a cool standalone environment monitor that displayed: temperature, humidity, pressure, altitude, forecast prediction, TVOC and CO2 levels (air quality), air quality status (good, moderate, or bad), and the IP address for the web page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/esp32-environment-monitor&quot;&gt;ESP32 Environment Monitor GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/esp32-environment-monitor/temperature-humidity.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/esp32-environment-monitor/top-view.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Around the same time I was acquiring the parts for the ESP32 environment monitor, I built another project with my dad that rotates a stepper motor to activate or deactivate an ultrasonic sensor in one of the industrial printers he was working on. It uses an ESP32-S3 WROOM on a breakout board, a Nema 17 stepper motor, and a motor driver to control the motor. After some iteration, we successfully made the motor move. The only problem is that the movement isn’t entirely accurate, and we believe it has faulty code, but we still haven’t had a chance to fix it. When it’s fixed, hopefully by the next blog post, I’ll try to show a video of the project working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/stepper-motor-project/stepper-motor-project.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently building a project with my brother that we believe has quite a bit of potential. It isn’t finished yet, and I would not like to disclose too much information here, but it is a really cool project. The next blog post might be in a few weeks, as I would like to talk about the project once it is up and running.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think during these next few months I will concentrate on this project I am building with my brother, and I would also like to come back to the rover and implement more AI models I plan on building. But I can’t really plan too far ahead, and I will see where the project with my brother takes me.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! During this past month after Shipwrecked, I have built an ESP32 environment monitor, completed a hardware project with my dad, and started a very interesting project with my brother.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/esp32-environment-monitor/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/esp32-environment-monitor/</guid></item><item>
        <title>Shipwrecked</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! This past weekend was one of the coolest experiences of my whole life. I shipped three projects in four days, and met some incredible people along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shipwrecked was a four-day hackathon on an island where 130 teenagers coded and shipped three projects for prizes. My brother and I were among the 130 teenagers who attended out of 5,000 who RSVPed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I get into the details, I’d like to say that the island was beautiful, and every activity and project was very well prepared and planned. I met many people and worked on three projects that I’m very proud of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/friends-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/friends-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/dock.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how did this Hackathon work? Each day you had to complete (ship) a project and present it in a science-fair style event showcasing all the projects built. If you met the project requirements, shipped it, and presented it, you earned a prize. During the day, few people felt like coding because there were so many workshops, challenges, and activities. Everyone ended up coding late at night, but it was worth it because going to these activities and challenges was really fun. Some examples include Zach’s workshop on how to create a non-profit, a spicy food challenge, a contest to build the tallest house, going swimming, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/basketball.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/tower.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1st-project&quot;&gt;1st Project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For first project, you had to build was a system to communicate without text, using things like colors, sounds, and images. I decided to work on it with a teammate who prefers not to be named, for this post, I’ll call him Byte, and Nikos (from Greece). We started brainstorming the first night and came up with a hardware project: four LEDs, each corresponds to a push-button, and each pair represents a feeling. The duration of the button press indicates the intensity of that feeling. For example, the green LED represents happiness, pressing its button for one second means you’re feeling sad, while pressing it for five seconds means you’re happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That night, I started designing the circuit and code in Tinkercad, finishing it by morning. After breakfast, we collected all the hardware parts needed for the project, although I had also brought my Arduino kit. Soon after, we started building the design, but we ran into a problem: the LCD screen didn’t work. Nikos and I tried for hours using the 4-pin LCD wiring method, but for some reason it just wouldn’t work. With only one hour left until the deadline to present our projects, we had to make an important decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/feeling-translator.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision came because our original plan was to use an ESP32 to transfer the button press data to an app Nikos was building. Unfortunately, Nikos couldn’t get the ESP32 working either. In retrospect, I regret not helping him with the ESP32, maybe the app could have been more complete. We had two options: (1) focus on hardware and hope the LCD screen worked before the deadline, or (2) focus on the app and make the same thing we were working on with the hardware in an app. We ended up doing both, kind of. I built the hardware, but instead of sending output to the LCD, it displayed in the Arduino IDE’s serial monitor. Meanwhile, Nikos built the app that was practically the same as what I had done in hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Nikos1508/Translator&quot;&gt;Feeling Translator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/1st-project.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once it was finished, we presented it, and the prize was a Hack Club shirt!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/merch/shirt.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2nd-project&quot;&gt;2nd Project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the second project you had to build something multiplayer, it could be a game, app, website… I decided to build this with Byte and Daniel (from Italy) and we started brainstorming right after the announcement. At the very start of the event, they gave us all PCB badges where we could flash it to display our name and handle, and they would receive announcements for events. But not only that, you could code it! We decided to try and build a game for the badges in which players pressed a button, and if two people pressed the same one, they were eliminated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/merch/badge.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the start, Byte and I focused on getting all three badges to connect, while Daniel worked on a simple UI for the app. But for some reason, the badges didn’t connect. When Daniel finished the UI he tried to help us troubleshoot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tried for hours, but the badges still wouldn’t connect. With only an hour or two left before the event, we decided to split into smaller teams. Byte kept trying to get the badges and the game to work, while Daniel and I tried to quickly build a website as our backup plan in case the badges still wouldn’t connect by presentation time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/v1ctorio/badge-game&quot;&gt;Badge Game&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/danielscos/russian-roulette&quot;&gt;Russian Rouletee&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/2nd-project.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, with a little help from AI, we managed to build a simple Russian roulettee game. On top of that, Byte also kind of got the badges to connect and the game to function properly. We rushed down to present our projects and came away with Shipwrecked stickers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/merch/stickers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3rd-project&quot;&gt;3rd Project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For our third and final project, we could build anything creative and colorful. I teamed up with Byte and Daniel, and we created a Chrome Extension that makes everything in your browser colorful and wild. At first, I thought it would be too difficult because we had so little time after all the day’s activities, but it turned out to be easier than I expected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In just an hour or two, we had a Chrome extension with a CSS file that overrode the site’s styles. Honestly, it looked pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/danielscos/browser-blaster&quot;&gt;Browser Blaster&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/3rd-project.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During this project, I learned how to create a Chrome extension.
Honestly, across all three projects, I also learned how to collaborate and how to distribute work with different people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That morning, we presented our projects and received Shipwrecked keychains as a reward!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/merch/keychain.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shipwrecked was an incredible experience, it was everything I could have expected and more. I met so many people who share my interests and had some really interesting conversations with them. The activities were amazing: I played basketball, flew a drone across the island, explored hidden beaches, and much more. One of the best friends I made during Shipwrecked is Imesh from Italy, who is a very kind and interesting person. Everyone was welcoming, and the island itself was beautiful. Thanks to everyone who made the event possible. I hope I can attend more Hackathons in the future!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/group-photo.JPG&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shipwrecked Video&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; margin: 2em 0;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uXWMr0gdLJA&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; style=&quot;display: inline-block; border-radius: 12px; box-shadow: 0 4px 12px rgba(0,0,0,0.1); overflow: hidden;&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;https://img.youtube.com/vi/uXWMr0gdLJA/0.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Shipwrecked Video&quot; style=&quot;width: 720px; max-width: 100%; display: block;&quot; /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;merch&quot;&gt;Merch&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/merch/t-shirt.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/merch/extra-stickers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/merch/light.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/merch/small-light.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/merch/map.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/merch/map-open.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Before &amp;amp; After: My laptop&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/merch/computer-without-stickers.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Laptop before stickers&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/merch/computer-with-stickers-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Laptop after stickers&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pictures&quot;&gt;Pictures&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/meetup.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/ferry.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/airplane.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/campfire.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/zach.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/island.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/sunny.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/view.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/sunny-boston.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/boston-sunset.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/hackathon/boston-night.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description><description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! This past weekend was one of the coolest experiences of my whole life. I shipped three projects in four days, and met some incredible people along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/shipwrecked/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/shipwrecked/</guid></item><item>
        <title>Arduino Security System</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! During this week, I designed and built my final project before Hack Club Shipwrecked: an Arduino Security System.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what does this security system look like, and how does it work?
It’s built on two separate breadboards, each with its own power supply. One of the breadboards holds the Arduino, which runs the code and manages the logic. The second, simpler breadboard contains the laser module, which can be connected to a slide switch to manually turn it on or off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main breadboard features:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One pushbutton for arming/disarming/shutting down the system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Three LEDs: green (armed), red (alert), and yellow (shutdown)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A piezo buzzer for the alarm&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A laser receiver&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system is designed to be completely standalone, with both breadboards powered through wall adapters, no need to stay connected to a computer.
In operation, the Arduino constantly checks the laser beam. When the beam is uninterrupted and hitting the sensor, it reads LOW. If the beam is broken, the input reads HIGH, which triggers the alarm and turns on the red LED.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After building the Arduino Simon Says game, I wanted to raise the bar. I decided a security system using a laser module and laser receiver would be the perfect next project. First, my dad and I ordered the necessary parts to make sure they’d arrive in time for me to build the system before Hack Club Shipwrecked. While waiting for the parts, I started designing the project in Tinkercad, but I quickly ran into a problem: Tinkercad doesn’t include laser modules or laser receivers as components. So I substituted the laser module with an LED and used a photoresistor in place of the laser receiver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/arduino/security-system-wiring-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After about a day of building, I had the Tinkercad hardware complete. Next, I started working on the code. I had to write two versions: one for the Tinkercad simulation using a photoresistor, and another for the real-life setup using a laser receiver. This way, the project could function both in the virtual environment and in real life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the physical components arrived, I started building the real-world version of the project. Unfortunately, time wasn’t on my side due to Shipwrecked being only a few days away. Thankfully, after a bit of trial and error, I managed to complete the project with a few days to spare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I tested the system, captured some photos and videos, and put together a simple demo video to showcase how it works, something required for hardware project that count towards Shipwrecked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; margin: 2em 0;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video controls=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%; border-radius: 12px; box-shadow: 0 4px 12px rgba(0,0,0,0.1);&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;https://raw.githubusercontent.com/adrirubio/arduino-security-system/main/my-build/demos/arduino-security-system-demo.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Your browser does not support the video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I finished up the README file, added some final touches to the project, and submitted it up for review. I’m very happy with how it turned out. I plan to install this security system next to my bedroom door to catch any unwanted intruders. The project took me about 7 hours and 30 minutes to complete which totals to around 75 dollars towards the stipend, which means that once approved, the total stipend will be nearly $290.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/arduino-security-system&quot;&gt;Arduino Security System&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/arduino/security-up-for-review.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I write this, Shipwrecked is just two days away, and I can’t wait! My next blog post will cover all the adventures and experiences from the event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/arduino/arduino-security-system-pic.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description><description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! During this week, I designed and built my final project before Hack Club Shipwrecked: an Arduino Security System.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/arduino-security-system/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/arduino-security-system/</guid></item><item>
        <title>Arduino Simon Says Game</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! Over the past two weeks, I began working with the Arduino kit, completed several projects from the book, and even created my own project that contributes to the Boston flight stipend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It didn’t take long for me to get absorbed in the world of electronics. I started watching videos on voltage, current, resistors, LEDs, and more. I quickly got familiar with the kit, installed the Arduino IDE, and added Hackatime to track my hours. Before I knew it, I was already working on the first project from the guidebook.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first project involved simply connecting one and then two LEDs, so I quickly moved on to the second one, which was wiring three LEDs to a pushbutton. This project gave me a basic but valuable understanding of how C++ and Arduino code work. I completed it soon after and was happy with the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/arduino/arduino-book-project-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The third project used a temperature sensor to measure the temperature of one of your fingers. The last project I worked on was the fourth, as the projects became more time consuming and I needed to focus on logging hours toward the flight cost. But I made sure to read through the remaining projects so I can better understand them moving forward. The fourth project involved three phototransistors, each designed to detect a color: red, green, or blue. These were connected to an RGB LED, which mixed the colors and displayed the result using some simple code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/arduino/arduino-book-project-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I had finished working with the guidebook, I decided to start one of the projects I had in mind: an Arduino Simon Says game. I began building it in Tinkercad but wrote the code in the Arduino IDE so it would count toward Shipwrecked. It took me about three days to complete the breadboarding and get the code working within the Tinkercad simulations. Once I was happy with the design and functionality, I built the physical version, which was up and running within a day. I made some small changes to the code at that stage, but nothing too big.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/arduino/wiring-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I was happy with the result, I began working on a demo video, since hardware projects especially require one to be accepted. I took plenty of video clips and screencasts, recorded audio, and even found a song in the YouTube Music Library. In a day or two, I had put together a demo video that I am quite happy with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arduino Simon Says Demo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; margin: 2em 0;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video controls=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%; border-radius: 12px; box-shadow: 0 4px 12px rgba(0,0,0,0.1);&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/arduino-simon-says/raw/refs/heads/main/my-build/demos/arduino-simon-says-demo.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Your browser does not support the video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I put together the README, added the finishing touches to the repo, and submitted the project for review. If it gets accepted, it would contribute to a grand total of 214 dollars, which is not bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/arduino/simon-up-for-review.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week, I plan to build a small project similar to this one, and then I’ll be off to Shipwrecked.
Also, feel free to check the GitHub repo out and read the README for more information on the project!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/arduino-simon-says&quot;&gt;Arduino Simon Says&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/arduino/arduino-simon-says-pic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description><description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! Over the past two weeks, I began working with the Arduino kit, completed several projects from the book, and even created my own project that contributes to the Boston flight stipend!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/arduino-simon-says-game/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/arduino-simon-says-game/</guid></item><item>
        <title>Retro Snake Game</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! This week, there was a change of plans. Instead of starting with the Arduino kit, I decided to complete one more project for Shipwrecked: a Retro Snake Game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The change of plans happened because the flight cost €500 per person, and since my dad, my brother, and I were all going, the total would have been around €1,500, which is quite a lot. So, I decided to do one last project before diving into the Arduino: a Retro Snake Game!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I get into the details of my Snake Game, you might be wondering: why was my brother also coming to Boston? Was he also working on Shipwrecked? Well, no, he was working toward something similar called Neighborhood, where, if you complete a working app in 100 Hackatime hours, you earn a chance to go to San Francisco for as long as you want. You get to stay in houses with people your age. Neighborhood was designed for 16, 17, and 18 year-olds. The only catch? You had to code at least 40 hours a week to stay in SF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan was for him to go from Boston to Neighborhood. The only problem? Well, Neighborhood was cancelled because too many teenagers met the requirements, and there weren’t enough houses to accommodate them all. In the end, the situation wasn’t ideal for the participants, and the best course of action was to cancel the program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since my brother already had a flight booked to Boston, he’s now looking for alternatives, possibly trying to go for Shipwrecked instead. He had completed 45 out of the 100 required Hackatime hours for Neighborhood, but with the program canceled, he doesn’t have much motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to do one more project because, for every hour you complete beyond the required 60 hours across four projects, you earn €10 toward your flight cost. To get those extra hours, I chose to build a Retro Snake Game. I spent the whole week working on it and only finished it yesterday. I logged 13 hours in total, which adds up to €130, though it still needs to be reviewed and accepted on the Shipwrecked page. Currently I have €32 from the little bits of hours from the other four projects. If I get my retro snake game accepted it would total to €162.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retro Snake Game Demo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; margin: 2em 0;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video controls=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%; border-radius: 12px; box-shadow: 0 4px 12px rgba(0,0,0,0.1);&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/ai-pdf-reader-demo/raw/main/retro-snake-game-demo.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/webm&quot; /&gt;
    Your browser does not support the video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/retro-snake-game/&quot;&gt;retro-snake-game github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.org/project/retro-snake-game/&quot;&gt;retro-snake-game-pypi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the next few weeks before Shipwrecked, I plan to focus on the Arduino kit. I’m also hoping to earn a bit more toward our flights, since Hackatime is compatible with the Arduino IDE, which means I can track hours spent on electronics projects for Shipwrecked. As I mentioned last week, I’ve got some great ideas that I can’t wait to get into.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! This week, there was a change of plans. Instead of starting with the Arduino kit, I decided to complete one more project for Shipwrecked: a Retro Snake Game.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/retro-snake-game/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/retro-snake-game/</guid></item><item>
        <title>Shipwrecked Invitation</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! The past two weeks have been a rollercoaster, but I’m proud to say that I’ve successfully completed 30 hours of work and built two full projects. All of my projects have been accepted, and I’m officially invited to Hack Club Shipwrecked!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Monday and Tuesday, I completed the QR-Gen project that I had previously started, and I’m quite proud of how it turned out. I also created a demo video of the finished product and updated the README with the full installation instructions and the demo.
Once the project was complete I put the project up for review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/qr-gen&quot;&gt;QR-Gen&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that kept me motivated during those long coding days was watching the leaderboard and seeing myself gradually climb up the ranks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/leaderboard.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;QR-Gen Demo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; margin: 2em 0;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video controls=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%; border-radius: 12px; box-shadow: 0 4px 12px rgba(0,0,0,0.1);&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/ai-pdf-reader-demo/raw/main/qr-gen-demo.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/webm&quot; /&gt;
    Your browser does not support the video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I began working on my final project, Text-Lens. The goal of Text-Lens is to analyze any given text and present a variety of insights through visual tools like diagrams, graphs, and advanced statistics. It breaks down the text’s structure and key characteristics to help users better understand and interpret written content. The destop app includes four core metrics: top words, sentence length analysis, punctuation breakdown, sentiment analysis, and some advaced stats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/text-lens&quot;&gt;Text-Lens&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the deadline approached, I realized I was still a few hours short, and doubt started to appear in my mind. But I pushed through those final hours and ultimately submitted my final project just in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Text-Lens Demo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; margin: 2em 0;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video controls=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%; border-radius: 12px; box-shadow: 0 4px 12px rgba(0,0,0,0.1);&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/ai-pdf-reader-demo/raw/main/text-lens-demo.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/webm&quot; /&gt;
    Your browser does not support the video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the next week I read the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ai-2027.com/&quot;&gt;AI 2027&lt;/a&gt; site and a few of the AI papers from my &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/ai-learning/blob/main/reading-list.org&quot;&gt;ai-learning&lt;/a&gt; list while I waited for the projects to get accepted. I found the AI 2027 site incredibly interesting as it offers a look into a possible future. I highly recommend reading it for both its insights and perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Wednesday, Architext-AI and QR-Gen were accepted. At that point, I was just one project away from being invited to Shipwrecked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/two-projects-accepted.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/three-projects-accepted.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, my final project was initially rejected because it wasn’t deployed using UV. So on Friday morning, I deployed the project on &lt;a href=&quot;https://pypi.org/project/text-lens/&quot;&gt;PyPI&lt;/a&gt;. Now, you can install it using either ‘pip install text-lens’ or ‘uv pip install text-lens’, and run it with the command ‘text-lens’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not long after, the project was accepted, and the following morning, I was officially invited to Shipwrecked!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/invited.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, my parents and I will start preparing everything for Shipwrecked (flights, accomodation, etc.). Over the next few weeks, I plan to dive into Arduino to learn more about digital electronics and breadboarding. I already have a few exciting project ideas in mind, and I’m really looking forward to start work on them!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! The past two weeks have been a rollercoaster, but I’m proud to say that I’ve successfully completed 30 hours of work and built two full projects. All of my projects have been accepted, and I’m officially invited to Hack Club Shipwrecked!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><pubDate>Sat, 05 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/shipwrecked-invitation/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/shipwrecked-invitation/</guid></item><item>
        <title>Finishing Architext-AI and starting QR-Gen</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! In this post, I&apos;ll take talk about the latest two weeks of my Shipwrecked adventure. From striving to hit 150 stars to receiving a message that changes it all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I left it off two weeks ago after just creating the Architext-AI project. I am proud to say that it is now complete, and I am quite pleased with the final result. The experience reminded me of some fun projects I built as a kid using Tkinter. It was quite nice for a young child to see an interesting UI with widgets and entry boxes, knowing he built them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finalizing the UI for the project, with some assistance from Claude and ChatGPT, I developed a Python script that sets the F5 key as the default key bind to automatically open the Architext-AI desktop app. You can find everything on my GitHub if you’d like to give it a try. I recorded my screen and created a short demo video, which I later converted into a GIF and uploaded to my GitHub. With that, I completed the 15-hour requirement for the second Shipwrecked project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned last week, Architext-AI is a straightforward message enhancer featuring a message input box and a prompt that serves as a guideline for the AI. I developed this small project because I need to complete four projects, each having at least 15 hours, with one achieving viral status to qualify for the Shipwrecked hackathon. During this time, my dad and I were actively posting on social media to see if the AI-PDF-Reader project (originally intended to go viral) could gain some traction. I am quite proud to report that, as of July 22, the AI-PDF-Reader has got 49 stars. It’s still 101 stars short of the 150 needed to attend Shipwrecked, along with the completion of the other three projects of at least 15 hours. However, all of this seems less significant now because two days ago, I read a message that changed everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/ai-pdf-reader&quot;&gt;AI-PDF-Reader&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/architext-ai&quot;&gt;Architext-AI&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Architext-AI Demo:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; margin: 2em 0;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video controls=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%; border-radius: 12px; box-shadow: 0 4px 12px rgba(0,0,0,0.1);&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/ai-pdf-reader-demo/raw/main/architext-ai-demo.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/webm&quot; /&gt;
    Your browser does not support the video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The message read the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;@channel this is biggest announcement EVER:
Finish your Shipwrecked project next week, earn a guaranteed invite (no need to go viral)!
If you complete your 4 projects with at least 15 hours each before next Sunday (June 29), we will waive the virality requirement for you and you’ll earn an invite to Shipwrecked!
You have until Sunday night to ship all your projects in The Bay to have your virality requirement waived!
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was instantly a game-changer. If the virality requirement were waived, it would save me a lot of effort—or would it? Achieving 30 hours in just over a week, when I read the message, would be no easy task. At the time, I had just finished the second project (Architext-AI) and was only halfway through. But, as with most things, I decided to give it a try. For the past two days, I have done practically nothing else but focus on accumulating as many hours as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now is probably a good time to mention the third project I’ve been working on for the past two days: the QR-Gen. This is a simple Tkinter project where you input text or a link, and it generates the corresponding QR code. I’ve also added a database feature to store past QR codes, and I think it’s looking nice. So far, I’ve accumulated 9 hours and 48 minutes of work, which isn’t bad for two days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have 20 hours of work to complete in the next six days to secure a guaranteed invitation to Shipwrecked, and I intend on making every hour count!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward to sharing my journey and the final results of the QR-Gen project next week, along with my next project!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post documents the state of the QR-Gen as of July 22, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
To see the current state of the project visit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/qr-gen&quot;&gt;qr-gen github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description><description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! In this post, I&apos;ll take talk about the latest two weeks of my Shipwrecked adventure. From striving to hit 150 stars to receiving a message that changes it all!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><pubDate>Sun, 22 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/finishing-Architext-AI-and-starting-QR-Gen/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/finishing-Architext-AI-and-starting-QR-Gen/</guid></item><item>
        <title>Starting Architext-AI</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! In this post, I wrapped up the AI PDF Reader by releasing a Windows version and started my next project — an AI writing assistant called Architext-AI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started the week by creating a demo video for the AI PDF Reader, which is now embedded in  &lt;a href=&quot;https://adrianrubio.org/blog/my-ai-pdf-reader-how-and-why-I-build-it/&quot;&gt;last week’s blog post.&lt;/a&gt; I’m really happy with how the final version turned out. To wrap up the project, I released a Windows version and improved the README.
Hopefully, the AI PDF Reader can gain some traction, as my dad and I will be sharing it across various social media platforms. Our goal is to reach 150 stars on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, I began brainstorming ideas for my next project. With some help from my dad, we came up with a simple Python program: using a predefined command, you can open a small window where write your message, and the AI will enhance it for you—improving clarity and overall quality. I think it would be something everyone would use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I got started on the project. I planned out the structure and chose &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.python.org/3/library/tkinter.html&quot;&gt;Tkinter&lt;/a&gt; for the GUI and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://openai.github.io/openai-agents-python/&quot;&gt;OpenAI SDK&lt;/a&gt; for the AI capabilites. I set up all the necessary files, and now I’m focusing on building the Python GUI. Hopefully, by next week, I’ll have something that looks good and works smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post documents the state of Architext-AI as of June 8, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
To see the current state of the pdf reader visit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/architext-ai&quot;&gt;architext-ai github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description><description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! In this post, I wrapped up the AI PDF Reader by releasing a Windows version and started my next project — an AI writing assistant called Architext-AI.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><pubDate>Sun, 08 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/starting-architext-ai/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/starting-architext-ai/</guid></item><item>
        <title>My AI PDF Reader: The Story of How (and Why) I Built It</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! In this post I&apos;m going to tell you the whole story of my AI PDF reader – like, how I built it and the reasons why. This project was a pretty wild ride with some tough challenges and fun wins, and seeing it finally work just how I wanted is awesome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a huge &lt;a href=&quot;https://karpathy.ai/&quot;&gt;Andrej Karpathy&lt;/a&gt; fan (the guy who invented the term &lt;em&gt;vibe coding&lt;/em&gt;) and pretty much watch all his videos. One time, while I was watching his “How I use LLMs” video, he said that he wished there was a tool to make reading PDFs way easier. That just clicked for me! I read a lot of AI papers (about how different AI systems are built), and I often get stuck on tricky parts. The idea of highlighting text and getting help right away to understand it? That sounded awesome!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He specifically imagined a tool where you could highlight text in the PDF and get AI explanations. He actually talks about the idea &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EWvNQjAaOHw&amp;amp;t=3507s&quot;&gt;right here!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I decided to give it a shot!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was my very first desktop app using &lt;em&gt;Electron&lt;/em&gt;, so for some of the harder parts, I &lt;strong&gt;vibe coded&lt;/strong&gt; it – you know, working with an AI (Claude 3.7 via &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cursor.com/&quot;&gt;Cursor&lt;/a&gt;) helping me along. I definitely used this chance to understand these frameworks better, and now they don’t seem as confusing as before! I also learned that &lt;em&gt;vibe coding&lt;/em&gt; isn’t as easy as it looks. You have to explain everything super clearly to the AI, and sometimes it would just get stuck, meaning I’d have to dive in and figure things out. Getting the UI to work was awesome! But sometimes trying to fix one tiny bug would just make a bunch of new ones pop up – so frustrating! Still, I learned a ton about &lt;em&gt;Electron,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;npm&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;JavaScript&lt;/em&gt;. I even got used to using Git branches, which was super helpful for trying new stuff without breaking everything. And when I had a stable version, I learned how to make GitHub Releases so people could actually download and use the app! Looking back it was a really great experience and I learned so much!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: center; margin: 2em 0;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;video controls=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;720&quot; style=&quot;max-width: 100%; border-radius: 12px; box-shadow: 0 4px 12px rgba(0,0,0,0.1);&quot;&gt;
    &lt;source src=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/ai-pdf-reader-demo/raw/main/ai-pdf-reader-demo.mp4&quot; type=&quot;video/mp4&quot; /&gt;
    Your browser does not support the video tag.
  &lt;/video&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really hope this can be a useful tool for students, researchers, or anyone who wants to read PDFs more efficiently.
You can find the project, download the app, and see all the code on my GitHub page: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/ai-pdf-reader&quot;&gt;AI PDF reader&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you think it’s cool or useful, starring the project on GitHub would mean the world to me! It helps other people find it and really motivates me to keep building new things. I’d also love to hear what you think or if you have any ideas!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading and checking out my project!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! In this post I&apos;m going to tell you the whole story of my AI PDF reader – like, how I built it and the reasons why. This project was a pretty wild ride with some tough challenges and fun wins, and seeing it finally work just how I wanted is awesome!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><pubDate>Sat, 31 May 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/my-ai-pdf-reader-how-and-why-I-build-it/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/my-ai-pdf-reader-how-and-why-I-build-it/</guid></item><item>
        <title>Improving the AI PDF Reader</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! Over the past two weeks, I’ve been working hard on the AI PDF Reader. I’ve improved the UI, integrated the AI API, and am now implementing a database to support the reader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t posted in the past two weeks as I’ve been fully focused on developing the AI PDF Reader. Now that I’ve found a moment, here’s a quick recap of what I’ve been working on and what to expect moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started the week by addressing several UI issues to make the interface cleaner and more user-friendly.
I removed the “Simple,” “Like I’m Five,” and “Technical” modes, keeping only the “Custom” option to streamline the experience. I also enlarged the chat area and slightly repositioned the PDF viewer to the left for better layout balance. Instead of dumping the entire highlighted text into the chat, it now generates a compact link or button that takes you directly to the relevant section in the PDF—making navigation much smoother. Additionally, when starting a new chat, it can now retain full context from the entire PDF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, I began integrating the API.
The app now supports OpenAI API keys, correctly detects them, and uses them for generating responses.
Here is a quick look at what’s changed from where we left off to this week:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/pdf-reader-home.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/pdf-reader-home2.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also added:
&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/full-context.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/chat-with-full-context.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I joined the Shipwrecked kickoff call and got to see what other teenagers are building. It was exciting to hear from other builders, share early progress, and get inspired by a wide range of creative ideas. Being part of a community like this adds an extra layer of motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, I’ve spent about 14 hours on the project. Once I finish implementing the database and polish things up a bit, I plan to launch a small web demo. After that, I’ll start promoting it across different platforms hopefully reaching 150 stars on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/shipwrecked/23.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post documents the state of the AI pdf reader as of May 18, 2025&lt;br /&gt;
To see the current state of the ai pdf reader visit:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/adrirubio/ai-pdf-reader&quot;&gt;AI pdf reader github&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description><description>&lt;p class=&quot;intro&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dropcap&quot;&gt;H&lt;/span&gt;ello and welcome! Over the past two weeks, I’ve been working hard on the AI PDF Reader. I’ve improved the UI, integrated the AI API, and am now implementing a database to support the reader.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><pubDate>Sun, 18 May 2025 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/blog/improving-the-ai-pdf-reader/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/blog/improving-the-ai-pdf-reader/</guid></item></channel>
</rss>
